Marcel Breuer
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Exhibition Files, 1922-1974, Series 9:; (Box 34, OV 49; Reels 5737-5738; 0.8 linear feet)
  - Royal Show, Bristol, England, Gane's Pavilion, 1936, 1963 (Box 34, Reel 5737)
    - Photographs of construction (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1015)
    - Photographs of completed project, exterior, (2 folders) (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1016-1024)
    - Photographs of completed project, interior (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1025-1027)
    - Clipping (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1028-1031)
  - British Cement and Concrete Association Exhibition, London, England, Garden City of the Future (Civic Center), 1936-1940 (Box 34, Reel 5737)
    - Photographs of plans (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1033-1034)
    - Photographs of models, (2 folders) (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1035-1052)
    - Negatives (Box 34, Reel unfilmed, Frame unfilmed)
  - Marcel Breuer and the American Tradition in Architecture, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1938 (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1053-1078)
    (typescript of exhibition catalog)
  - New York World's Fair, Flushing Meadows, New York, Pennsylvania Pavilion, 1939 (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1079-1099)
    (photographs of plans and completed installation)
  - Low Cost Furniture Competition, Museum of Modern Art, New York, New York, Cutout Plywood Chair, 1948 (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1100-1110)
    (photographs of drawing and completed chair)
  - Museum of Modern Art Exhibition, New York, New York, House in Museum Garden, 1949 (Box 34, Reel 5737)
    - Photographs of plans and drawings (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1112-1117)
    - Photographs of completed installation, exterior (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1118-1123)
    - Photographs of completed installation, interior, (2 folders) (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1124-1138)
    - Negatives and color transparencies (Box 34, Reel unfilmed, Frame unfilmed)
    - Clippings (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1139-1154)
  - Tile Council of America Exhibition, New York, New York, Patio-Bathroom, 1953 (Box 34, Reel 5737)
    - Photographs of completed installation, interior (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1155-1162)
    - Clipping (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1163-1164)
  - Good Design Exhibition, Museum of Modern Art, New York, New York, Hyperbolic Paraboloid, 1955-1957 (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1165-1169)
    (photographs of installation and individual objects)
  - International Autumn Fair, Vienna, Austria, U.S. Pavilion, 1957, (letters) (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1170-1177)
  - Amerika Baut (America Builds) Exhibition, Marshall House, Berlin, Germany, 1957 (Box 34, Reel 5737)
    - Photographs of installation (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1179-1180)
    - Exhibition catalogs (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1181-1190)
  - Ars Sacra Exhibiton, Louvain, France, 1958 (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1191-1192)
    (receipt for photographs of Breuer projects)
  - Concrete Industries Exposition, Cleveland, Ohio, The Pavilion, 1958-1959 (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1193-1208)
    (receipts; clipping; exhibition catalog)
  - U.S. Architecture in Moscow, Moscow, U.S.S.R.: press release; clipping, 1959 (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1209-1215)
  - 1960 National Gold Medal Exhibition of the Building Arts, Architectural League of New York, Museum of Contemporary Crafts, New York, New York, 1959-1960, (Oversized material housed in OV 49) (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1216-1282)
    (photographic displays of various Breuer projects; prospectuses; exhibition catalogs; original drawing for exhibition of photographs)
  - Oversized +1960 National Gold Medal Exhibition of the Building Arts, Architectural League of New York, Museum of Contemporary Crafts, New York, New York, 1959-1960, (Oversized material scanned with Box 34, Reel 5737, Frames1216-1282) (Box OV 49, Reel 5737)
  - Form Givers at Mid-Century, Time Magazine (traveling exhibition): Photographic Displays of Various Breuer Projects, 1959-1961 (Box 34, Reel 5737)
    - Notes including exhibition itinerary and list of projects; shipping receipt (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1284-1288)
    - Photographs of installation (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1289-1291)
    - Program and clippings (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1292-1298)
    - Exhibition catalogs (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1299-1332)
  - Bauhaus [location unknown]: exhibition catalog, 1961 (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1333-1345)
  - New Forms in Concrete, American Federation of Arts (traveling exhibition), 1961-1964 (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1346-1358)
    (photographic displays of various Breuer projects; notes, including an exhibition itinerary and list of comments about the exhibition; a shipping receipt; clippings)
  - Fourth Biennale of Present-Day Christian Art, Salzburg Dome, Salzburg, Austria, 1962 (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1359-1363)
    (letter; receipt listing photographs of St. John's Abbey)
  - Recent American Synagogue Architecture, Jewish Museum, New York, New York, 1963 (Box 34, Reel 5737, Frame 1364-1374)
    (letter; shipping receipts listing photographs and models of various religious properties designed by Breuer)
  - Churches and Temples: Postwar Architecture, American Institute of Architects, Pepsi Cola Gallery, New York, New York, 1963-1964, (letter; prospectus; exhibition catalog) (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 15-31)
  - On Campus: Recent Buildings, American Federation of Arts (traveling exhibition), 1963-1964 (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 32-41)
    (notes including exhibition itinerary and list of comments about the exhibition; press release; clippings)
  - Art in the United States, Part III (Architecture in the U.S.A.), Brearley School, New York, New York, 1964 (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 42-54)
    (photographic displays of various Breuer projects; memorandum; shipping receipts listing photographs; blueprint of layout of photographs of New York University; exhibition catalog)
  - Architecture of Industry, Architectural League of New York, (traveling exhibition), 1965-1967 (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 55-61)
    (exhibition itinerary; shipping receipt; clippings)
  - Svoboda & Company Furniture Exhibition Selection 66, Vienna, Austria, 1966, (photographs of installation) (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 62-67)
  - School of Architecture Exhibition, University of Oklahoma, Norman, Oklahoma, 1966 (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 68-71)
    (letter; shipping receipts listing photographs of projects)
  - Rugs, Stephen Radich Gallery, New York, New York, 1966, (exhibition announcement; clipping) (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 72-74)
  - Bauhaus: A Teaching Idea, Carpenter Center for the Visual Arts, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1966-1967 (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 75-77)
    (loan agreement)
  - Le Bauhaus: 1919-1969, Musée National d'Art Moderne et Musée d'Art Moderne de la Ville de Paris, Paris, France, 1969 (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 78-80)
    (exhibition announcement)
  - [Marcel Breuer] Szépmuvészeti Múzeum (Museum of Fine Arts), Budapest, Hungary, 1970 (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 81-85)
    (list of slides of projects; shipping receipt)
  - Breuer en France, Knoll International, Paris, France, 1972 (Box 34, Reel 5738)
    - Letters including notes and address lists, (2 folders) (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 87-217)
    - Photograph of Breuer (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 218)
  - Marcel Breuer at the Metropolitan Museum of Art (traveling exhibition), Metropolitan Museum of Art New York, New York, 1972-1975 (Box 34, Reel 5738)
    - Photographs of installation, (4 folders) (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 221-253)
    - Catalog List (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 254-280)
    - Exhibition catalogs (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 281-286)
    - Clippings (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 287-310)
  - Museum of Science and Industry, Chicago, Illinois, 1973-1974 (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 311-315)
    (photograph of Breuer at exhibition opening; clipping)
  - Centre de Création Industrielle, Pavillon de Marsan, Musée des Arts Décoratifs, Paris, France, 1974, (exhibition catalog; clippings) (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 316-347)
  - Bauhaus-Archiv, Berlin-Charlottenburg, Germany, 1975, (exhibition catalog; clippings) (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 348-366)
  - The Flowering of American Folk Art, Whitney Museum of American Art, New York, New York, Installation Designed by Breuer and Hamilton Smith, 1974 (Box 34, Reel 5738)
    - Photograph of floor plan (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 368-369)
    - Photographs of installation, (4 folders) (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 370-401)
    - Acousti-Guide script (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 402-423)
    - Clippings (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 424-430)
  - Art and Contemporary Architecture, David Findlay Galleries, New York, New York, 1977, (exhibition catalog) (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 431-448)
- Photographs, 1928-1979, Series 10:; (Boxes 34, 41-42; Reel 5738; 0.3 linear feet)
  This series contains photographs of Breuer and his family and colleagues. Three photograph albums are of dozens of architectural projects. Researchers will find photographs of Breuer interacting with his colleagues including Alexander Calder, Naum Gabo, and Walter Gropius.
  The series is organized into five chronologically arranged subseries.
  10.1: Photographs of Breuer and Mrs Breuer, 1928-1979
  10.2: Photographs of Breuer with Friends and Colleagues, 1938-1978
  10.3: Photograph Albums of Architectural Projects, 1947-1970
  10.4: Miscellaneous Photographs, 1961
  - Photographs of Breuer and Mrs. Breuer, 1928-1979, 10.1:
    - Portrait photographs of Breuer, including two by Tamás Breuer, 1928-1979, (3 folders) (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 450-493)
    - Passport Photograph of Mrs. Breuer, 1966 (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 494)
  - Photographs of Breuer with Friends and Colleagues, 1938-1978, 10.2:
    Photographs 1938-circa 1940 include Breuer with friends in Concord, Massachusetts, 1938; Herbert Bayer, Marian Willard, Ise Gropius, Ati Gropius in Breuer House, Lincoln, Massachusetts, circa 1940; Constance Breuer, Dottie Noyes, and Christopher Tunnan; Breuer with Mercedes Matter, Konrad Wachsmann, and Alexander Calder; and Breuer with Joan McVitty, Edward Larrabee Barnes, Mary Barnes, and Alexander Calder in Breuer House I, New Canaan, Connecticut.
    Photographs 1955-1958 include Breuer with Matta at UNESCO cocktail party, 1957; Breuer with Walter Gropius in Paris for UNESCO. Photographs 1958-1961 include Breuer with George Salle in Paris, 1958; Breuer with Eduardo Catalano in Argentina; Breuer on a jury with unidentified South American colleagues, on a panel with unidentified colleagues and in Philip Johnson's house, 1961.
    Photographs 1961-1978 include Breuer with Eric Boissonnas and Flaine Architects at Hunter College, 1961; at a reception with Dino Gavina in Milan, 1962; Breuer on a panel at College of Architecture and Design, University of Michigan, with Chet LaMore, David Reider, Robert Iglehart, and William Muschenheim, 1963; Birthday party [80th birthday of Walter Gropius?], 1963; Breuer on jury for R. S. Reynolds Memorial Award, 1965, with William Stephen Allen, George Harrell, Vernon DeMars, and Mario Pani; Breuer with Yuichiro Kojiro at Breuer House II in New Canaan, Connecticut, 1966; Breuer receiving the George Washington Award at American Hungarian Studies Foundation ceremony, Plaza Hotel, New York, 1967.
    - Photographs of Breuer with Friends and Colleagues, circa 1938-circa 1940 (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 496-501)
    - Photographs of Breuer with Friends and Colleagues, 1955-1958 (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 502-511)
    - Photographs of Breuer with Friends and Colleagues, 1958-1961 (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 512-543)
    - Photographs of Breuer with Friends and Colleagues, 1961-1978 (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 544-575)
  - Photograph Albums of Architectural Projects, 1947-1970, 10.3:
    - Album I, 1947-1956, undated, 10.3.1:
      - Thompson House, 1947 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 578-584)
      - Kniffin House, 1948 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 585-589)
      - Vassar College Dormitory, 1949 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 590-594)
      - Clark House, 1949 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 595-599)
      - Pack House, 1950 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 600-604)
      - Wolfson Trailer House, 1950 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 605-611)
      - Hanson House, 1950 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 612-614)
      - Rufus Stillman House I, 1950 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 615-620)
      - Sarah Lawrence College, 1951 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 621-631)
      - Breuer House II, 1951 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 632-640)
      - Caesar House, 1951 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 641-645)
      - Neumann House, 1952 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 646-652)
      - St. John's Abbey and University, 1953 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 653-655)
      - Litchfield Schools, model, 1953 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 656-660)
      - Torrington Factory, Canada, 1953 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 661-665)
      - Princeton University Housing, Institute for Advanced Study, model, 1954 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 666-668)
      - Grieco House, 1954 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 669-675)
      - Annunciation Priory, Convent, model, and New London Station, 1954-1955 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 676-678)
      - Starkey House, 1954 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 679-685)
      - St. John's Abbey, Monastery Wing, undated (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 686-690)
      - Gagarin House I, undated (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 691-697)
      - Litchfield High School, 1953 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 698-706)
      - Hunter College Library, model, 1955 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 707-709)
      - De Bijenkorf Department Store (23 photographs are by Robert Doisneau), 1953 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 710-740)
      - Institute for Advanced Study, Members' Housing Project, undated (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 741-745)
      - St. John's Abbey Church and Bell Tower, model, 1956 (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 746-748)
      - New Haven Railroad trains, undated (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 749-755)
      - Torrington Manufacturing Company, California, undated (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 756-760)
      - Laaff House, undated (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 761-763)
      - New York University, Bronx Campus, undated (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 764-770)
      - St. John's Abbey, undated (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 771-779)
      - New York University, Bronx Campus, undated (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 780-784)
      - Scarves by Vera, Los Angeles, undated (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 785-787)
      - Staehelin House, undated (Box 41, Reel 5738, Frame 788-794)
    - Album II, 1953-1970, 10.3.2:
      - Fairview Heights Housing, 1961-1964 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 796-798)
      - Torrington Manufacturing Plant, Nivelles, Belgium, 1963-1964 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 799-801)
      - Scarves by Vera, 417 Fifth Avenue (4 photographs are by André Kertész), 1965 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 802-803)
      - Torrington Administration Building, Torrington, Connecticut (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 804-806)
      - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1963-1966 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 807-819)
      - Rufus Stillman House II, 1965 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 820-822)
      - Franklin Delano Roosevelt Memorial, 1966 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 823-824)
      - St. Francis de Sales Church (one photograph is by Marcel Breuer), 1961-1967 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 825-831)
      - St. John's Abbey and University, 1953-1968 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 832-848)
      - Housing and Urban Development Headquarters Building, 1963-1968 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 849-855)
      - ZUP Project, 1963-1967 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 856-862)
      - Geller House II, 1959-1969 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 863-866)
      - New York University, Bronx Campus, Technology Building II, 1967-1969 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 867-874)
      - University of Massachusetts Campus Center and Parking Garage, 1965-1970 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 875-877)
      - Mary College, 1965-1968 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 878-883)
      - Flaine Ski Resort Town, 1969 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 884-888)
      - Armstrong Rubber Company, 1965-1970 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 889-891)
      - IBM, Boca Raton, Florida, 1967-1970 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 892-896)
      - Yale University, 1965-1970 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 897-900)
      - Laboratoires Sarget, undated (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 901-906)
    - Album III, 1965-1970, 10.3.3:
      - Cleveland Museum of Art, 1967-1970 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 908-919)
      - Cleveland Trust Company, undated (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 920-929)
      - University of Massachusetts Campus Center and Parking Garage, 1965-1969 (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 930-934)
      - Baldegg Convent, undated (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 935-939)
      - Scrapbook of Printed Material (Box 42, Reel 5738, Frame 940-1159)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, 1961, undated, 10.4:
    - Photo-collage of an unidentified Hispanic festival; photographs of architectural details in Greece, 1961, undated (Box 34, Reel 5738, Frame 1160-1163)
- Printed Material, 1925-1984, Series 11:; (Boxes 35, 42; Reels 5738-5739; 1.0 linear ft.)
  This series has been divided into 8 chronologically arranged file groups, according to the type of material. Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others includes material relating to Nadia Benois; Lyonel Feininger, 1936; László Moholy-Nagy, 1940; Decima Triennale di Milano, 1954; American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1959; Eric Rutherford, 1964; "Erfahrungen, Strukturen, Imaginationen" group exhibition with André Bloc, Hans Glaube, Sergius Ruegenberg, and Eckhard Schulze-Fielitz, 1965; Sidney Wolfson, 1965; Fred Woell and Hui Ka Kwong, 1967; Robert and Ella Bergmann Michel, 1968; and Walter Gropius, 1970. Miscellaneous Printed Material includes rosters of registered architects in Connecticut (1951 and 1971) and Who's Who Among Professionals of Hungarian Origin in the Americas (1961).
  - Clippings, 1925-1951, undated (Box 35, Reel 5738, Frame 1167-1308)
  - Clippings, 1952-1955 (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 12-81)
  - Clippings, 1956-1961 (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 82-251)
  - Clippings, 1962-1968 (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 252-598)
  - Clippings, 1969-1970 (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 599-752)
  - Clippings, 1971-1973 (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 753-816)
  - Clippings, 1974-1984 (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 817-954)
  - Scrapbook of Tearsheets Concerning Architectural Projects, 1961-1970 (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 955-1175)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1936-1965, undated, (2 folders) (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 1176-1228)
  - Press Releases, 1955-1981, undated (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 1229-1270)
  - Prospectuses, 1952-1965 (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 1271-1314)
  - Calendars of Events, 1962-1968 (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 1315-1347)
  - Brochures (Box 35, Reel 5739)
    - Brochures for Schools, 1938-1939, undated (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 1349-1357)
    - Brochures for Publications, 1955-1971 (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 1358-1382)
    - Miscellaneous Brochures including a large Gavina brochure containing Breuer designs, 1937-1965, undated, (2 folders) (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 1383-1479)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1951-1971, undated, (2 folders) (Box 35, Reel 5739, Frame 1480-1500)